<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An abstract of common principles of a just vindication of the rights of the kingdom of God upon earth against the politick machinations of Erastian hereticks out of the Vindication of the deprived bishops, &amp;c. / by a very learned man of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22791</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12622575</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12622575</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64555</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61414)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64555)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 335:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An abstract of common principles of a just vindication of the rights of the kingdom of God upon earth against the politick machinations of Erastian hereticks out of the Vindication of the deprived bishops, &amp;c. / by a very learned man of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens (Socrates Christianus). Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dodwell, Henry, 1641-1711. --  Vindication of the deprived bishops.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Temporal power.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64555:1"/>
            <p>AN ABSTRACT OF <hi>Common Principles</hi> OF A Juſt Vindication OF THE RIGHTS OF THE Kingdom of God Upon EARTH, Againſt the <hi>Politick</hi> Machinations of <hi>Eraſtian</hi> Hereticks; Out of the <hi>Vindication of the Deprived Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. By a very Learned Man of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:64555:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64555:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Kingdom of God upon Earth</hi> is in its Inſtitution, and in its own Nature, really a Glorious Kingdom, tho', through the ill Adminiſtration of thoſe to whom it hath been committed, it hath never yet appeared in its true and proper Luſtre, and at preſent not only ſeems to be, but really is in a divided, ſhattered, and dejected condition. God in great Wiſdom doth very often with great Bodies of Men, as he doth with particular Perſons, put them to School to the Miſtreſs of Fools, leave them to eat the Fruit of their own doings, and to learn Wiſdom by their own Experience; to experiment and even feel the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of Humane Powers, the Deceitfulneſs of Humane Wiſdom, the Malice, Subtilty and Power of their Inviſible Adverſaries, and the Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his Goodneſs, the Infallibility of his Wiſdom, and the Irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of his Power; and their own intire Dependance upon Him, and abſolute need of continual Supply of all theſe from Him, and of conſtant Subjection and Conformity thereunto. If Men would therefore at last, after ſo long Experience, open their Eyes, lift up their Heads, and well conſider the Admirable Wiſdom of his Divine Inſtitution, the Excellent Accommodation of it for the Good and Benefit of Mankind; and of all Degrees, Orders, States, and Conditions amongst them; and how and by what Ways and Means it hath come to paſs that the World hath been ſo little ſenſible of, and received no more Benefit from ſo powerful and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual a Divine Favour, as the Inſtitution of this Kingdom is, and would have produced long ſince, had it been improved as it ought; and laſtly conſider, every one in his place, but eſpecially they who are in chief Places in Church or State, what <hi>the Intereſt</hi> of this bleſſed Kingdom, and the glorious King thereof, do require of all, and of themſelves in particular, for their own Good, and the common Good of all, and then, without more a-do, apply themſelves with full Reſolution to order all their Actions in Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity thereunto, and to approve their <hi>Fidelity</hi> to their Soveraign and his Interest, as becomes Good Subjects, they would ſoon perceive and receive
<pb facs="tcp:64555:3"/>the Benefit thereof, and behold it in its Glory. And tho' there is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent little appearance of any ſuch Diſpoſition in thoſe, who are firſt in place, that they will be forwardeſt in ſuch Actions, yet whoever will heartily do their part in this, as there is none but may do ſomething, ſo there is nothing that they can do ſo mean, if they do all they can, but will obtain a Glorious Reward, far above all this World can afford. But it will require no little <hi>Courage, Generoſity, Magnanimity</hi> and <hi>Conſtancy</hi> to perform it: for ſuch is the Nature and Terms of <hi>true Loyalty</hi> in this Kingdom, as will ſhake off Multitudes of Pretenders, when they come for Admittance. Yet it is, in ſhort, but firſt to diſpoſe themſelves for the receiving of Truth, and then, when fairly propoſed, cordially imbrace it, own and profeſs it, ſtick to it, and act accordingly. For the first of theſe there is lately printed a ſhort <hi>Recipe:</hi> and ſome of the most important and fundamental Truths for this purpoſe are here treated in the following <hi>ABSTRACT</hi> by a very Learned Man of the <hi>Church of England</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law, and a great and zealous Champion for it. It is true, it is but an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, but an <hi>Abſtract</hi> of what is very hard to be met with, and of the very Marrow of it, the rest being only critical Learning, of little or no uſe to the greatest part of even intelligent Readers; but only for Scholars, and ſuch as are curious in Matters of little moment. And for ſuch as deſire to ſee more to this purpoſe, they may have recourſe to a Learned Book of <hi>the Sinfulneſs and Miſchief of Schiſm,</hi> in <hi>40.</hi> and another in 8vo. of <hi>One Altar, and One Prieſthood,</hi> beſides a ſpecial Learned <hi>Defence of this Vindication,</hi> much more common to be had than the <hi>Vindication</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>More was intended concerning <hi>this Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>true Subjects</hi> of it, for the proper <hi>Uſe</hi> and <hi>Application</hi> of this Catholick Doctrine; but becauſe it may be more ſeaſonable when the Doctrine hath been received and digeſted, it may be ſufficient here to add only this <hi>Admonition:</hi> That <hi>Separation from Separatiſts</hi> is no Separation from the <hi>One Body</hi> and <hi>Unity</hi> of this Kingdom: Nor is <hi>Viſible</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> inconſiſtent with Schiſmatical; but a <hi>Schiſmatical Communion</hi> may be really both, and hath been heretofore; nay, most <hi>viſible</hi> in the ſame City or Country, and truly <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> (tho' what is not ſo cannot but be Schiſmatical) and, beſides all this, <hi>Eſtabliſhed by Law.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64555:3"/>
            <head>Common Principles Of a juſt Vindication of the Rights of the Kingdom of God Upon EARTH, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>That for</hi> Clergy-Men <hi>to appear in a Cauſe deſtructive of the Intereſt of</hi> Religion <hi>in general, and of their own</hi> Function <hi>in particular, is inexcuſable.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THAT the <hi>Laity</hi> ſhould be favourable to Miſtakes dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to the <hi>Sacred</hi> Power, cannot be thought ſtrange in an Age wherein they generally uſe ſo little Diligence to inform themſelves, or to receive Information from thoſe who are qualified to inform them, concerning the Rights of the <hi>Clergy:</hi> Their own Intereſts are alone ſufficient to make them <hi>partial</hi> in affairs of this nature, tho' they were more ſincerely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced by Conſiderations of Religion, than we generally find them: But that <hi>Clergy-Men</hi> ſhould alſo favour them in Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on their <hi>own Function;</hi> that <hi>they</hi> ſhould profeſſedly patronize Doctrines tending to leſſen the Eſteem of that <hi>greatest and most valuable of all Authorities</hi> wherewith God has honoured and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted none but <hi>them,</hi> that they ſhould make it depend on the <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> which was deſigned for greater and more noble Ends than the <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> it ſelf; that they ſhould put it in his Power to deſtroy the very <hi>Being</hi> of the Church, as a <hi>Society,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64555:4"/>by a ſecular Deprivation; that they ſhould not only <hi>Own,</hi> but <hi>Teach,</hi> That none are obliged to adhere to <hi>themſelves</hi> in ſuch a Caſe wherein the <hi>Magiſtrate is against them,</hi> no not ſo much as in regard of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> that they ſhould by this means make the <hi>greatest and most momentous Concerns for Souls</hi> ſubordinate to <hi>Worldly, Carnal</hi> Politicks, and the far leſs weighty Intereſts of <hi>Worldly</hi> Proſperity, and of <hi>particular</hi> Societies; that they ſhould hereby make it <hi>least</hi> capable of ſubſiſting under a <hi>Perſecution,</hi> which was the Caſe moſt obvious in the View of our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and therefore moſt particularly provided for, if they took care for any thing beyond their own time: Theſe things, I ſay, would not be very credible, if they were not very notorious. One would think none who valued the general good of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and the <hi>Souls</hi> of Mankind, before the temporal Proſperity of any particular State, (and it is hard to conceive how any good Man can do otherwiſe) could even <hi>wiſh</hi> ſuch Opinions true, tho' his <hi>Wiſh</hi> alone were ſufficient to make them ſo. How then is it agreeable, that <hi>Clergy-Men</hi> of all Men ſhould be the moſt favourable and zealous <hi>Advocates</hi> for ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſo manifeſtly deſtructive of thoſe greateſt Intereſts, which they of all Men ought beſt to underſtand, and to be moſt zealouſly concerned for? How is it agreeable, that they of all Men cannot be content to let the <hi>Memory</hi> of <hi>ill Preſidents</hi> die, but that they muſt alarm us with future Fears of having them acted again by not only <hi>Abetting,</hi> but alſo <hi>Juſtifying</hi> them? How is it agreeable, that they ſhould do this in a <hi>Proſpect,</hi> ſuch as ours is, of a <hi>Laity</hi> ſo little <hi>concerned</hi> for the Good of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Church;</hi> when even they who have any Principles, have ſuch <hi>lax</hi> ones, and ſo very little obliging them, even in <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to venture any thing for any <hi>particular Communion?</hi> That their preferring their <hi>Worldly</hi> Concerns, depending on the Pleaſure of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> before the <hi>greater</hi> Concerns of <hi>Souls,</hi> and <hi>Eternity,</hi> is the true Cauſe of it, is not to be believed, while there are any <hi>Reaſons</hi> that might induce them to it. Yet <hi>little Reaſons</hi> cannot in <hi>Equity</hi> excuſe, when the <hi>Conſequences</hi> ought to be ſo very <hi>valuable</hi> on that very account of <hi>Mens</hi> being either <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Religious.</hi> Much leſs when the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the Principles on which they proceed are ſuch in reſpect to the <hi>Publick Intereſts</hi> even of their own Church, as put it in the Power of a <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> Prince (and even of a <hi>ſecret Infidel</hi> or <hi>Apoſtate</hi>) to diſſolve it when they pleaſe. Suppoſe a <hi>Popiſh
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64555:4"/>Prince,</hi> with a <hi>Popiſh Parliament,</hi> ſhould turn their Principles (that is, the Principles of theſe Men) againſt themſelves, and deprive all our <hi>Biſhops</hi> with one Act of <hi>State,</hi> I cannot ſee what theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers can pretend to ſecure their <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society,</hi> and as a <hi>Communion,</hi> in Oppoſition to them. They muſt ho longer pretend to <hi>Dioceſſes</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> They muſt not pretend to any <hi>Obligation</hi> of their <hi>Proteſtant Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laity</hi> to ſtand by them, even in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> They muſt therefore never pretend to <hi>Communions</hi> in <hi>thoſe Dioceſſes,</hi> which are plainly <hi>Exerciſes</hi> of <hi>Spiritual Authority</hi> in them. Nor can they then juſtifie, or even excuſe, any <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> for <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> when forbidden by the <hi>Civil</hi> Magiſtrate, who is <hi>only</hi> ſuppoſed, by <hi>theſe</hi> Principles, to have alſo the <hi>Right</hi> to that <hi>Spiritual</hi> Authority by which <hi>alone</hi> they can be juſtified. And are theſe the ways to <hi>ſecure</hi> our <hi>Religion</hi> againſt <hi>Popery?</hi> No open <hi>Perſecutions</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can ever ruine us ſo effectually as theſe <hi>Doctrines</hi> will, if ever we receive them. <hi>Doctrines</hi> of our <hi>own</hi> will break our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> among our <hi>ſelves,</hi> more than any of our Adverſaries open Violencies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>That the</hi> Church of Chriſt <hi>is not to be conſidered meerly as a</hi> Sect, <hi>but as a</hi> Sacred Society; <hi>and that its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a</hi> Society <hi>is a Fundamental Doctrine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MEN (amongſt us in this and the laſt Age) have hitherto conſidered the <hi>Church</hi> rather as a <hi>Sect,</hi> than as a <hi>Society;</hi> and have therefore uſually had no regard to the <hi>Doctrines Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> to it as a <hi>Society,</hi> if they did not withall concern it as a <hi>Sect,</hi> and <hi>Antecedently</hi> to its being a <hi>Society.</hi> But there ſeems very little Reaſon for their doing ſo, if they will be pleaſed impartially to reflect on it. It is very true, its Notion as a <hi>Sect</hi> is <hi>antecedent</hi> to its being a <hi>Society,</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>Society</hi> into which Men find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged to enter by the <hi>Doctrines</hi> they muſt be ſuppoſed to believe, if they own it as a <hi>Sect.</hi> But even thence it appears, that the <hi>Doctrines</hi> which concern it as a <hi>Sect,</hi> do withall make it <hi>neceſſary</hi> it ſhould be a <hi>Society.</hi> Theſe two Conſiderations therefore are by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64555:5"/>no means to be ſeparated. Nay, it hence appears, that the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> conſtituting it as a <hi>Sect,</hi> do alſo by a near, and unavoidable, and evident <hi>Conſequence,</hi> make it a <hi>Society.</hi> Thus therefore the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of its being a <hi>Society,</hi> will be included in that <hi>Syſtem</hi> of <hi>Doctrines</hi> which concern it as a <hi>Sect.</hi> And then what Matter is it that <hi>one</hi> of theſe <hi>Notions</hi> is <hi>antecedent,</hi> and the <hi>other, conſequent?</hi> Thus much at leaſt will follow, that there is no <hi>ſubverting</hi> it as a <hi>Society,</hi> without <hi>ſubverting</hi> it alſo as a <hi>Sect;</hi> becauſe thoſe very <hi>Doctrines</hi> which make it a <hi>Sect,</hi> do alſo conſequently oblige it to be a <hi>Society.</hi> For my part, I believe thoſe <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which all who believe any <hi>Fundamentals</hi> proper to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Religion, as <hi>Revealed</hi> by God, do reckon among <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> not to have been revealed for <hi>Speculation</hi> only, but purpoſely to oblige Men to <hi>unite</hi> in it as a <hi>Society.</hi> The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in <hi>Trinity,</hi> which is the principal thing inſiſted on in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as <hi>revealed</hi> in the Scripture, was purpoſely to let Men ſee the <hi>Extent</hi> of the <hi>Myſtical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> to which they were intitled by the <hi>External <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>viſible Church,</hi> that by partaking in the <hi>Orthodox Communion,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> mentioned by St. <hi>John,</hi> they had alſo a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. For it was manifeſt they muſt alſo partake of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> becauſe he who had not <hi>the Spirit of Christ was none of his.</hi> It was therefore ſuppoſed, that by partaking of the <hi>Trinity</hi> we are made one <hi>Myſtically,</hi> and that by being <hi>united viſibly</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> we are intitled to that <hi>Myſtical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> So whoever is united <hi>viſibly</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> is thereby, if he be not wanting to himſelf in due Conditions, united alſo <hi>Myſtically</hi> to the <hi>Trinity;</hi> and that whoever is <hi>divided</hi> exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally from the <hi>Church,</hi> is thereby alſo <hi>diſ-united</hi> from this <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>Trinity.</hi> And what more <hi>prevaeiling In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements</hi> could be thought of to oblige Men to keep in a <hi>Society?</hi> So alſo the deſign of the <hi>Incarnation</hi> was, by <hi>Christ</hi>'s taking upon him our <hi>Body</hi> and our <hi>Fleſh,</hi> to make <hi>us</hi> alſo <hi>one Body</hi> and <hi>one Fleſh</hi> with <hi>Him,</hi> thereby to entitle our <hi>Bodies</hi> to a <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> but then our being <hi>one Body</hi> and <hi>one Fleſh</hi> with Him, depended on our being <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> which is called <hi>his Body, his Fleſh, his Bones.</hi> We were to be <hi>Baptized</hi> into this <hi>one Body,</hi> and become <hi>one Body,</hi> by partaking of <hi>one Bread.</hi> Which plainly ſhew that all the <hi>Benefits</hi> of the <hi>Incarnation</hi> are derived to us by our partaking of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and therefore by our <hi>adhering</hi> inſeparably to them who alone are <hi>authorized</hi> by God to <hi>adminiſter</hi> them. Thus plain it is that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64555:5"/>thoſe very <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of our revealed Religion, as revealed, are revealed and deſigned for this purpoſe of making the <hi>Church</hi> a <hi>Society.</hi> How can therefore our Adverſaries make theſe Doctrines <hi>Fundamental,</hi> if this be not <hi>Fundamental</hi> alſo, that the <hi>Church</hi> was by God deſigned to be a <hi>Society?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This at leaſt is certain, that we are intitled to all the Benefits of our Religion, by our owning the <hi>Church</hi> not only as a <hi>Sect,</hi> but as a <hi>Society</hi> alſo; and that tho' we believe all its Doctrines as it is a <hi>Sect,</hi> yet if we be divided from it as a <hi>Society,</hi> that Belief alone will not ſecure us a Title to any of the Benefits of our Religion. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicates,</hi> however Orthodox in their Opinions, were never ſuppos'd, in the Diſcipline of the Church, to have any actual Title to the Benefits of Religion, if they perſiſted wilfully in that State of <hi>Excommunication.</hi> The ſame is to be obſerved concerning the Caſe of <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> on the Principles of the early Age of St. <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Hence therefore it appears, that this Notion of the <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society,</hi> whatever it be in its ſelf, is at leaſt Fundamental as to us, in order to our partaking of any of the Benefits of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: That is, indeed it is Fundamental to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes that we can think worthy our Enquiry. Without this, the other Notions, if any be, will never be beneficial to us. So that whatever thoſe other Notions may be, in order of <hi>Reaſoning;</hi> yet this Notion of the <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society,</hi> muſt be Fundamental to them in order to their being beneficial; <hi>that is,</hi> as far as we have any reaſon to concern our ſelves for them. Theſe things ought cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to be taken for Fundamental, as to the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the Church. She ought certainly to be moſt concerned for thoſe things that are moſt influential on the Intereſts of Souls; and thoſe are ſo whoſe Belief is moſt beneficial, and their Diſ-belief moſt hurtful to thoſe moſt valuable Intereſts. I cannot therefore ſee why ſhe ſhould not think Doctrines of this kind Fundamental, and reckon them among thoſe Fundamentals on which ſhe ought to lay out her principal Care. If therefore ſhe ought to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate for any Errors at all, certainly ſhe ought in the firſt place to do it for Errors ſo deſtructive of all Obligation to her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion it ſelf, and of her Authority of Excommunicating; <hi>that is,</hi> indeed ſo deſtructive to all that <hi>Power</hi> ſhe has either for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of <hi>Truth,</hi> or the Prohibition of <hi>Error</hi> in general. And if ſhe ought not to inflict her <hi>Cenſures,</hi> at leaſt theſe higheſt of them, for any Errors but thoſe which are Fundamental; it will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64555:6"/>plainly follow, that Errors of this kind muſt be reckoned for Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental ones. Our Adverſaries would have Errors in Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals publiſhed, and puniſhed as a <hi>Spiritual</hi> Crime, by a purely <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> Authority; but they do not, in the mean time, ſeem to be aware how Fundamental this very Notion of the <hi>Church,</hi> as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and ſpiritual <hi>Society,</hi> is to its having any <hi>Authority,</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> to puniſh ſo much as Spiritually. All they can do as a <hi>Sect,</hi> is only to reaſon with <hi>Hereticks</hi> concerning their <hi>Errors;</hi> and all the <hi>Means</hi> to reduce them are thoſe reaſons which can no farther pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with them than as they may ſeem convictive in the Judgment of the <hi>Hereticks</hi> themſelves. But on that account they ſtand on even Terms with the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> whoſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> ought alſo to take place with the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks,</hi> ſo far as they are alſo in Conſcience convinced by them. A true <hi>Authority,</hi> and a <hi>Power</hi> of puniſhing refractory Perſons, by <hi>excluding</hi> from <hi>Communion,</hi> do Fudamentally ſuppoſe a ſpiritual <hi>Society</hi> over which they are to exerciſe this Authority, and from which Delinquents are to be excluded by ſpiritual <hi>Cenſures</hi> and <hi>Excommunications.</hi> How can they therefore avoid reckoning thoſe <hi>Errors</hi> from being <hi>Fundamental</hi> ones as pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by a <hi>ſpiritual Authority,</hi> which ruine Fundamentally that very <hi>Authority</hi> by which ſuch <hi>Errors</hi> are to be puniſhed; which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Society</hi> on which that <hi>Authority</hi> is grounded <hi>Fundamentally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there be degrees of <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> I ſhould think the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals concerning the <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society,</hi> to be of the greateſt conſequence, and therefore Fundamental in the higheſt degree. The Church is indeed obliged to keep the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16.</note> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſe are the Expreſſions by which our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries themſelves, I believe, conceive the Articles themſelves call <hi>Fundamental</hi> to be ſignified. But ſhe is obliged to keep them as a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20.</note> as a Truſt committed to her. How ſo? by avoiding <hi>Diſputings,</hi> by ſtopping the Mouths of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> by rebuking them with all <hi>Authority,</hi> by rejecting and avoiding not their <hi>Doctrines</hi> only, but their <hi>Perſons</hi> alſo, when they prove incorrigible. Now theſe things plainly ſuppoſe Governors inveſted with <hi>Spiritual</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and a <hi>Communion</hi> from whence incurable <hi>Hereticks</hi> are to be rejected. So that in order to the keeping theſe other <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society,</hi> is ſuppoſed antecedently as a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that alone can qualifie her for having ſuch a <hi>Trust</hi> committed to her. This Notion therefore as antecedent muſt be Fundamental to thoſe other Fundamentals, and therefore Fundamental in a higher
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64555:6"/>ſenſe than thoſe things can be whoſe Security is ſuperſtructed upon it. And accordingly the Damage of the Publick in ſubverting theſe Notions of the <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society,</hi> is proportionably greater than that which follows from the denial of other particular Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which are commonly taken for Fundamental. He that denies one of the other Articles, may yet believe all the reſt, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly defend them, and that by Principles too, againſt all other <hi>Hereticks.</hi> But he that denies the <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society,</hi> inveſted with a <hi>ſpiritual Authority,</hi> does as effectually contribute to the Ruine of all the other Fundamentals at once, as he does to the Ruine of a Houſe, who ſubverts the Foundations of it. It brings in <hi>Impunity</hi> for <hi>Hereſie</hi> in general, and ſuffers <hi>Hereticks</hi> ſtill to hope as well in their ſeparate Sects, as if they were in the Orhtodox Communion. It leaves them deſtitute of even any Preſumptions that might oblige them to judge in Favour of the Church's Doctrine, as the ſafeſt Error, if it ſhould prove one. It does by this means reduce the trial of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> to the <hi>Reaſons</hi> themſelves, and their native Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and puts it in the Power of aſſuming Men to pretend greater Evidence than either they have, or they really believe. And things being reduced to this paſs, it is more God's Providence, than the Security of Principles, that hinders any <hi>Heretick,</hi> who diſputes any one of the other Articles, from queſtioning all the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>That the contrary Doctrine is a</hi> Fundamental Error, <hi>and obſtinately aſſerted</hi> Hereſie, <hi>very pernicious to the Church of Chriſt, and to the Aſſertors of it themſelves.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ST. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> obſerves, that <hi>Schiſms</hi> generally end in <hi>Hereſie:</hi> That is the natural conſequence of <hi>Defending</hi> it, as our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries do, by <hi>Principles.</hi> A ſingle Act of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndutifulneſs</hi> to <hi>Superiors</hi> will in courſe paſs away with thoſe who are guilty of it; ſo that Poſterity will not be concerned in it: But when it is defended by <hi>Principles,</hi> it turns into <hi>falſe Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> of that perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Conſequence, that the <hi>Church</hi> is obliged to take notice of it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64555:7"/>as ſhe will be faithful to her Truſt, in ſecuring her <hi>Body</hi> from the like Diviſions for the future. Thus the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> took the firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for their <hi>Schiſm</hi> from the pretended <hi>Perſonal</hi> Faults of <hi>Caeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> and his Ordainers. This, whilſt it was a <hi>particular Caſe,</hi> went no farther than that <hi>particular Schiſm:</hi> But when it turned into a <hi>general Doctrine,</hi> that <hi>Perſonal</hi> Faults were ſufficient to juſtifie <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> then it laid a Foundation of <hi>frequent Schiſms,</hi> as often as any <hi>Criminals</hi> got into Places of <hi>Trust,</hi> and either <hi>Evidence</hi> was wanting, or <hi>themſelves</hi> too powerful to be conteſted with: Then it concerned Eccleſiaſtical Governours to <hi>condemn</hi> this Doctrine, that encouraged even Men of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to divide deſignedly and frequently. And when that Doctrine was thus condemned by the <hi>Church,</hi> and was notwithſtanding maintained by the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> as a <hi>Principle</hi> on which they ſubſiſted as an <hi>oppoſite Communion,</hi> it then became a Character of a <hi>Party</hi> to maintain it, and from that time forward the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were reckoned among <hi>Hereticks,</hi> as well as <hi>Schiſmaticks:</hi> For this was the true Notion of <hi>Hereſie</hi> in thoſe Ages, as contradiſtinct from <hi>Schiſm:</hi> Both of them ſuppoſed a <hi>Diviſion of Communion,</hi> or tended to it. But that <hi>Diviſion</hi> was called <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which only broke the <hi>Political <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the <hi>Society,</hi> without any difference of <hi>Principles;</hi> as when <hi>Thieves</hi> or <hi>Robbers</hi> tranſgreſs their Duties without any pretence of <hi>Principles</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing them to do ſo. So whilſt <hi>Reſentment</hi> alone was the reaſon that made <hi>Subjects</hi> ſeparate from the <hi>Communion</hi> of their Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Governours, or whilſt <hi>Ambition</hi> alone made any to invade the Office of his <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and to erect an <hi>oppoſite Communion,</hi> this was <hi>Schiſm</hi> properly ſo called, as contradiſtinct from <hi>Hereſie.</hi> But when the <hi>Schiſm</hi> is patronized by <hi>Doctrines,</hi> and juſtified as well done, and conſiſtently with Conſcience; ſuch <hi>Diviſions,</hi> beſides their being <hi>Schiſmatical,</hi> were <hi>Heretical</hi> alſo in the ſenſe of the Ancients, and ſuch <hi>Doctrines,</hi> as <hi>Characteriſtical</hi> of a diſtinct <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> were properly called <hi>Hereſies.</hi> On this account the ſame <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the original Identity of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> was no <hi>Hereſie</hi> in S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> who notwithſtanding kept Communion with the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the <hi>Juriſdictions</hi> he lived in; and yet was <hi>Hereſie</hi> in <hi>Aaerius,</hi> when upon account of that pretended <hi>Identity</hi> he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to pay no more Duty to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the reſpective <hi>Juriſdictions,</hi> than he would have done to ſingle <hi>Presbyters.</hi> This is the moſt agreeable account of the <hi>Hereſies,</hi> not only in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtrius,</hi> but in other more judicious Collectors of <hi>Catalogues</hi> of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64555:7"/>
                  <hi>Hereſies.</hi> And it is very agreeable with the Notion of that Term among the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> from whom the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> derived it. All <hi>Notions</hi> that were proper and characteriſtical to particular Schools among them made <hi>Hereſies,</hi> not thoſe which were received n com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among them. Anſwerably whereunto thoſe Differences only in <hi>Opinion</hi> made <hi>Hereſies</hi> in the Church, which were the Notes of different Communions, not thoſe which went no farther than Speculation.</p>
               <p>I am very well aware how ſurprizing this will be to thoſe who, upon popular Opinions, have uſed to believe no Opinion <hi>Hereſie</hi> that was not againſt Fundamentals. But if they will for a while lay aſide their Prejudices, they will poſſibly find this as ſlightly grounded as many other popular Opinions are. The very diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between <hi>Fundamentals</hi> and <hi>Non-Fundamentals,</hi> is not, that I know of, ever taken notice of by the Primitive Chriſtians, either in the ſame, or in equivalent Terms. And if a Perſon will needs make a <hi>Breach</hi> on account of an <hi>Opinion,</hi> it rather aggravates than diminiſhes his Guilt, that the Opinion is of little conſequence: His own <hi>Will</hi> is more concerned in it; <hi>that is,</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and he is therefore more a <hi>Heretick,</hi> and, as <hi>Hereticks</hi> were, more <hi>ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, Tit.</hi> 3.2. if, even in his own Opinion, the Matter for which he ſeparates be not of any conſiderable Importance. Even a <hi>Truth,</hi> and a <hi>Truth</hi> that has great Evidence of its being ſo, may make a <hi>Hereſie,</hi> if it be no way conducive nor diſadvantageous to the good of Souls; and yet the Perſon who maintains it will by no means endure Communion with thoſe who are of another Mind. He might have more pretence of <hi>Zeal,</hi> tho' Miſtaken, if the Miſtake on the Church's ſide did indeed concern Souls, and ſeemed, at leaſt, of dangerous conſequence to them. When he has not even <hi>that</hi> to pretend for himſelf, who can impute his breaking on ſuch accounts to any other Original than an aſſuming <hi>Imperiouſneſs</hi> of Temper, and a love of <hi>Contention,</hi> which we generally acknowledge to be the principal Ingredients of <hi>Hereſie?</hi> Certain it is, that ſuch a <hi>Breach</hi> for <hi>Opinions,</hi> tho' true, yet of no conſequence, is highly cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, and deſtructive to that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> which Chriſt deſigned for his Church, and the more culpable for that very reaſon, that the <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> is of little conſequence. Yet it cannot properly be called <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which is only a <hi>Breach,</hi> like thoſe which fall out frequently in Secular Affairs, when Men fall into Parties, on account of a Temper ungovernable, or ambitions, without any proper difference
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64555:8"/>of <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Doctrine.</hi> And it being no <hi>Schiſm,</hi> what can we call it in the Diſcipline of the Church, if it be not <hi>Hereſie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Opinions</hi> therefore which are not otherwiſe <hi>Heretical</hi> on account of the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Opinions</hi> themſelves, do then begin to be <hi>Heretical</hi> when they begin to be characteriſtical of <hi>diſtinct Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions.</hi> And that they do, not only when Men deſignedly ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from others on that very account, becauſe they are not of the ſame <hi>Opinions;</hi> but alſo when they venture on ſuch Practices on account of their ſingular <hi>Opinions,</hi> wherein others cannot communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with them, for that very reaſon becauſe they cannot join with them in thoſe their ſingular <hi>Opinions.</hi> Then plainly the differing in ſuch <hi>Opinions,</hi> makes a difference of <hi>Communion</hi> unavoidable; and therefore the <hi>Opinions</hi> themſelves, in ſuch a Caſe as this is, are <hi>Signals</hi> of different <hi>Communions,</hi> which will come under the charge of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> as contradiſtinct from <hi>Schiſm,</hi> in the Notion now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed of the Primitive Church. Thus, had S. <hi>Hierome</hi> proceeded as far as <hi>Aerius</hi> in the Practice of his Opinion concerning the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal <hi>Identity</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and had thereupon broken himſelf off from his <hi>Duty</hi> to the Biſhop of the Dioceſe, and by that means either made or countenanced a <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which he had never countenanced but on account of this Doctrine of his which he held in Common with the <hi>Aerians,</hi> that Doctrine had been <hi>Hereſie</hi> in him, as well as the <hi>Aerians.</hi> So alſo Opiuions do then begin to be Treaſonable, when they are actually productive of Treaſonable Actions. Thus <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> Opinions in the <hi>Church</hi> do always weaken or diſſolve the <hi>Obligation</hi> in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to maintain the <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society,</hi> in a time of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> from the <hi>Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate;</hi> yet till that Caſe fall out, and when <hi>Intereſt</hi> lies on the <hi>Church</hi>'s ſide, they often ſtill keep one <hi>Communion</hi> who are for ſuch Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and may continue in it while there are any other Inducements to keep them in it beſides thoſe of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Only it may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be fit to be conſider'd, whether it be prudent to truſt ſuch Perſons with the Management of the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> who have no Obligation of <hi>Principles</hi> or <hi>Conſcience</hi> to maintain it as an <hi>independent Society,</hi> or to ſuffer for it; <hi>that is,</hi> indeed who are never likely to maintain it in that very Caſe which was moſt in our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> View; <hi>that is,</hi> of a <hi>Perſecution.</hi> But when they actually divide that Communion which they were never obliged in Conſcience to maintain, if they took the utmoſt Liberty their <hi>Latitudinarian Principles</hi> would afford them; and when their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64555:8"/>lax Principles are the very grounds of their dividing the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion without any remorſe of Conſcience for doing ſo; when they are hereby emboldned to do thoſe things which inevitably cauſe a Breach from thoſe who cannot follow them in theſe very Principles. This is the Caſe wherein theſe Principles are Characters of a <hi>diſtinct Communion;</hi> and therefore, by the <hi>Reaſoning</hi> now mentioned, become <hi>Heretical:</hi> Eſpecially the Principles being withall falſe, not only in the Opinion of thoſe from whom they have divided themſelves, but alſo of our earlieſt pureſt Anceſtors, even thoſe of the Apoſtolical Age it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Yet I deny not but that in this Caſe of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> there is alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to be had to the Momentouſneſs of the Opinion it ſelf. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſets up or abets a Communion oppoſite to that of the Church, on account of <hi>Opinions,</hi> is, as I have ſhewn, in the Judgment of the Primitive Church, an <hi>Heretick;</hi> and is the more, not the leſs ſo, if the <hi>Opinions</hi> be alſo frivolous. But for ſuch Opinions the Church would never have driven him out of her own Communion, if him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had been pleaſed to have continued in it. Her <hi>Judiciary Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> ought, no doubt, to be confined to Opinions Fundamental and of great Importance; eſpecially if an internal Aſſent be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and that under pain of <hi>Excommunication.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>That the</hi> Church of Chriſt <hi>is a</hi> Society <hi>independent on any of the Powers of the World; and its</hi> Spiritual Rights, <hi>derived immediately from a higher Authority, ſubject to none of them, according to the Doctrine of the Catholick Church in the earlieſt Ages.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>EVEN in the Age of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> (which is the ancienteſt we know of that an <hi>Anti-Biſhop</hi> was ſet up againſt a Biſhop in the ſame See) it is, 1ſt, very notorious, that they then owned no ſuch Power of the Secular Magiſtrate to deprive Biſhops of their purely Spiritual Power; and that the <hi>Church,</hi> as a <hi>Society</hi> diſtinct
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64555:9"/>from the <hi>State,</hi> ſubſiſted on their not owning it, even as to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of their particular <hi>Diſtricts</hi> and <hi>Juriſdictions.</hi> It is noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and as notorious as any one Tradition of the Catholick Church in thoſe Ages, (not excepting that of the Canon of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> it ſelf) that Chriſtians then, and not only then, but in all the former Perſecutions that had been from the times of the Apoſtles to that very Age, did own themſelves bound to adhere to their Biſhops, when it was notorious withall, that thoſe Biſhops were ſet up and maintained againſt the Conſent of the Civil Magiſtrate. It is as notorious alſo, that this Adherence of theirs was not only Matter of Fact, (which is all our Adverſaries pretend here) but a Duty owned by them, as obliging in Conſcience, and as the reſult of Principles. This appears, not only by the unqueſtionable Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of the Chriſtians of thoſe Ages, who were generouſly influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced by no Conſiderations but thoſe of Conſcience; not only by their Suffering thoſe ſevere Penances impoſed on them, in order to their recovering the Biſhop's Communion, even when the Magiſtrate was againſt him, which no other Conſiderations could recommend, but only thoſe of Conſcience: but from the Principles themſelves inſiſted on in the <hi>Reaſonings</hi> of St. <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Such were theſe: That all hopes of <hi>Pardon of Sin,</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> of <hi>Eternal Life on Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Duty,</hi> were confined to the viſible Communion of the Church; that their viſible Communion with the Church could not appear but by their viſible Communion with the Biſhop, as the Head of that Church, and the Principle of its Unity; that who that Biſhop was, to whom any particular Perſon owed his Duty, was not then any otherwiſe diſtinguiſhable, but by the viſible Diſtricts in which themſelves lived, and to which he was therefore ſuppoſed to have a Title, whether the Magiſtrate would or no. It is alſo as notorious, that theſe <hi>Reaſonings</hi> were not then the ſenſe of private Perſons, but the received ſenſe of Chriſtians in general, and indeed Fundamental to that <hi>Catholick Communion,</hi> which was then main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained where-ever there were Chriſtians. Not only every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Chriſtian of a Dioceſs did thus aſſure himſelf of his Right to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Privileges, by his Communion with the Biſhop of that particular Diſtrict; but he was intitled alſo to Communion with all the other Biſhops of the World, and conſequently with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church in general, by the <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of his own particular Diſtrict. For it was by the mutual Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation all Biſhops of the World had to ratifie the Acts of particular
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64555:9"/>Diſtricts, that he who was admitted a Member of one Church, was intitled to the Communion of all; and that he who was excluded from one, was excluded from all others alſo; becauſe no other Biſhop could juſtifie his Reception of a Chriſtian of another Juriſdiction to his own Communion, if he had not the <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> of his own Biſhop. Thus it appears, that the Obligation, even of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Diſtricts</hi> without Conſent of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> was then <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctrine.</hi> Whence it plainly follows, that this <hi>Lay-deprivation,</hi> which is all that can be pretended in the Caſe of our preſent Biſhops, is, in the Principles of the Catholick Church in St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Age, a perfect <hi>Nullity,</hi> and conſequently that, in regard to Conſcience at leaſt, our preſent Biſhops are ſtill Biſhops, and Biſhops of thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Diſtricts, as much as ever; and the Obligations of the Clergy and Laity in thoſe Diſtricts, as obliging to them now as ever.</p>
               <p>And it thence follows, 2dly, that <hi>Anti-Biſhops,</hi> conſecrated in <hi>Diſtricts,</hi> no otherwiſe vacated than by the Power of the Secular Magiſtrate, are, by the Principles of that earlieſt Catholick Church, no Biſhops at all, but divided from the Church. It is plain, that <hi>Novatian</hi> was diſowned as ſoon as ever it appeared that <hi>Cornelius</hi> was canonically ſettled in <hi>Fabian</hi>'s Chair before him, and diſowned univerſally, ſo univerſally, that who-ever did not diſown him, was for that very reaſon diſowned himſelf. This is as clear as any Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular mentioned in our Adverſaries Collection. But we do not ſatisfie our ſelves with that. It is alſo further as notorious, that he was diſowned by Principles obliging them in Conſcience to diſown him, and thoſe again not private Opinions, but Principles alſo Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental to the Correſpondence then maintained in the whole Catholick Church, as the other were that we mentioned under the former Head. It was then a Principle, that
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 55. ad Antonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, <hi>Edit.</hi> Oxen, <hi>Cypr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Secundus</hi> was <hi>Nullus,</hi> which will as much invalidate the Conſecrations of the preſent Anti-Biſhops, as it did that of <hi>Novatian.</hi> This is a Principle ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally acknowledged, where-ever there can be but one, that it needs no Authorities to recommend it. No Man can convey the ſame thing twice: and therefore if there be two Bonds for the ſame thing to ſeveral Perſons, the ſecond can never be thought obliging, but by ſuppoſing the Invalidity of the firſt. So alſo in all Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Diſtricts, none can ſuppoſe an Anti-Monarch's Title good, till he has ſhewn that the firſt Monarch's Title is not ſo. Thus this Principle needed no Authority, and yet it had all the Authority of the whole Catholick Church of that Age. The whole <hi>Collegium</hi> of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64555:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Catholick Biſhops (that is St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Term) gave their <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatory Letters,</hi> not to <hi>Novatian,</hi> but <hi>Cornelius;</hi> and received none to their own Communion on the <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> of <hi>Novatian,</hi> but only on thoſe of <hi>Cornelius.</hi> And that upon this ſame common Principle, that <hi>Cornelius</hi> being once <hi>validly</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome, Novatian</hi> could never be a Biſhop of that ſame Diſtrict without the Death, or Ceſſion, or Deprivation of <hi>Cornelius;</hi> and that ſuppoſing him no Biſhop of that Place to which he was conſecrated, he could be no Biſhop at all. So far they were then from our late Fancy, of a <hi>Biſhop of the Catholick Church</hi> without a <hi>particular Diſtrict.</hi> Had they thought ſo, they might have ratified <hi>Novatian</hi>'s Acts, as a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, becauſe he had received his Power from Biſhops, tho' not as Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Comparing the Catholick Church to a <hi>Fanum,</hi> or Temple, he was <hi>Profanus,</hi> as not being in the Temple, nor having a Right to enter into it. Comparing it to the Houſe in which the Paſſover was to be eaten by the <hi>Jews,</hi> he was <hi>Foris,</hi> not in that Houſe, in which alone the Paſſover was to be eaten. Theſe were the Notions of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and were by him and his Colleagues un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> in general, when they all ſuppoſed <hi>Novatian</hi> out of the <hi>Catholick</hi> in general, by being out of that particular Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> of which he had formerly been a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Juſt as in ordinary Excommunications, they alſo always ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that he who was by any Act of obliging Authority deprived of his Right to his own particular Church, had alſo loſt his Right thereby to all the particular Churches in the World. And they alſo ſuppoſed <hi>Novatian</hi> to have caſt himſelf out of his own Body, by aſſuming to himſelf the Name of a <hi>Head</hi> of that Body, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready had a Head, and could have no more than one. And theſe Notions, and this Language of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> were ſuppoſed and owned univerſally by the whole Body of the Catholick Biſhops of his Time, when they acted conſequently to them, and took them for the Meaſures, by which they either granted or refuſed their own Communion. Nor is it to be thought ſtrange, that theſe Notions ſhould be received, and received univerſally, not as the Opinions of private Perſons, but as the publick Doctrine, and Fundamental to the Catholick Communion, as practiſed not only in that early Age of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> but as derived from the Apoſtles themſelves, and the very firſt Originals of Chriſtianity: For theſe were not, (as private Opinions uſually were) only the reſult of private Reaſonings; they were received as the Fundamentals of Chriſtianity, (which were not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64555:10"/>as new Revelations generally were,...) from <hi>the like Notions</hi> received among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and among them received not as private Opinions, but as publick Doctrines, and Fundamental to the then practiſed Sacrifical Communion of the then peculiar People, and only thence deduced (as other things alſo are, in the Reaſonings of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi>) to the Caſe of the new <hi>Myſtical Peculium,</hi> and their new <hi>Myſtical Sacrifices.</hi> The Language of erecting <hi>Altar</hi> againſt <hi>Altar</hi> in St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> is derived from the like earlier Language re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived among the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Diſcourſe of one Altar, <hi>&amp;c. Edit. Lond.</hi> 1683. 80.</note> concerning the <hi>Samaritan Altar</hi> of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> againſt the <hi>Jeruſalem Altar</hi> of <hi>Jaddus,</hi> that is, of a <hi>High Prieſt</hi> againſt a <hi>High Priest,</hi> when God had appointed but one High Prieſt in the whole World, and him only at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And it is alſo plain, that the Body of the <hi>Jews</hi> did look on ſuch Schiſmatical High Prieſts, and all their Communicants, as cut off from the Body of their <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culium,</hi> and conſequently from all their publick Sacrifices, and all the Privileges conſequent to them. Why ſhould we therefore think it ſtrange, that the Apoſtolical Chriſtians ſhould have the like Opinion of them, who ſet up themſelves as oppoſite Heads of their Myſtical Sacrifices?</p>
               <p>But this is not all. It is further as notorious, 3dly,
<note place="margin">St. <hi>Cyp.</hi> Epiſt. 43. Edit. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
                  </note> that all who any way profeſſed themſelves <hi>one with Novatian,</hi> were for that very <hi>Reaſon</hi> of their doing ſo, taken for divided from the Catholick Church, as well as he was with whom they were united. Here alſo the reaſon was very evident, that he who profeſſed, and, by publick Profeſſion, made himſelf one with a Perſon divided, muſt, by the ſame Analogy of Interpretation, profeſs himſelf divided, and, by that very Profeſſion, actually divide himſelf alſo, by making himſelf one with the Perſon ſuppoſed to be divided. Nor was this reaſon more evident, than univerſally acknowledged in the Diſcipline of that Age. All ſuch Uniters with the Schiſmatick were refuſed to be admitted to Communion, not by particular Biſhops only, (as the Caſe would have been if the Opinion had been ſingular) but by all the Biſhops of one Communion in the World.</p>
               <p>Not only ſo: But it is alſo as notorious, 4thly, from the Practice and Diſcipline of that Age, that all whom they looked upon as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <hi>Novatian,</hi> they conſequently looked on as divided from themſelves: To be ſure, in the firſt place, thoſe who had any hand in his pretended Conſecration, which were principally and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly reflected on by <hi>Cornelius,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Fabius</hi> of <hi>Antioch.</hi> Nor would his People be receiv'd to Communion by any Catholick
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64555:11"/>Biſhop on the <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> of <hi>Novatian;</hi> and they could expect none from <hi>Cornelius</hi> whilſt they were divided from him. Thus all his Subjects came to be involved as well as himſelf. But that which was higheſt of all was, that even Biſhops were ſuppoſed to have divided themſelves from their Brethren, if they communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with him; <hi>that is,</hi> if, according to the cuſtom of that Age, they either gave <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> to him, or receiv'd any to their own Communion on the like <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> receiv'd from him. This appear'd plainly in the Caſe of <hi>Martian</hi> of <hi>Arles,</hi> who was on this very account denied the <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> of his Brethren; and would, no doubt, have appeared alſo in the Caſe of <hi>Fabius</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> if he had proceeded ſo far. And this does plainly ſuppoſe, that ſuch Biſhops alſo had cut themſelves off from <hi>Catholick Communion</hi> by their own Act. And by this means it alſo appeared to have been more than a private Opinion in that Age, when even no Biſhop could be permitted in the Communion of his Brethren, if he diſſented from them in this particular. Thus, to make <hi>Application</hi> to our preſent Caſe, all the Biſhops will be invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, who communicate either with the <hi>Principal Schiſmaticks,</hi> or the <hi>Schiſmatical Conſecrators.</hi> And this will alſo take in, by the ſame Principles, all Communicants with ſuch Biſhops. For when the Biſhop was refuſed Communion, the Effect of ſuch refuſal was, that none ſhould thence-forwards expect to be received to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thoſe who had refuſed him on his <hi>communicatory Letters;</hi> and no other <hi>communicatory Letters</hi> could be hoped for whilſt they continued in Communion with him.</p>
               <p>And then, 5thly, it is alſo as notorious, on the ſame Principles of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Age, that ſuch <hi>Schiſm</hi> from the viſible Communion of the Catholick Church, was alſo ſuppoſed to deprive the Perſon ſo divided of all the inviſible Benefits of <hi>Church Communion.</hi> God was ſuppoſed obliged to ratifie in Heaven, what was done by thoſe whom he authorized to repreſent Him on Earth. He avenged the Contempts of his Miniſters, and would not be a Father to thoſe who would not own his Church for their Mother, by paying her a Filial reſpect. They were not to expect any Pardon of their Sins: They could not hope for the Holy Ghoſt, who diſſolved the Unity of the Spirit:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Cypr. de Unitate Eccl. <hi>Ep.</hi> 49. <hi>Edit.</hi> Ox. <hi>Ep.</hi> 52, 54, 55.</note> They were uncapable of the Crown of Martyrdom, whatever they ſuffered in the State of Separation. This is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of many of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Diſcourſes on this Argument: And indeed it is very agreeable with the Deſign of God, that they who
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64555:11"/>cut themſelves off from the <hi>Peculium,</hi> ſhould, by their doing ſo, loſe all their pretenſions to the Rights and Privileges of it. Not only ſo, but that they ſhould alſo incurr all the Miſchiefs to which they were ſuppoſed liable, who had loſt their Right of being Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the peculiar People. Accordingly as they believed all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, at their firſt Admiſſion into the Church, to be turned from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God; ſo upon their leaving the Church, or their being caſt out of it by the judicial act of their Superiors, they were ſuppoſed to return into the State of Heathens, to loſe the Protection of thoſe good Spirits who miniſter only to the Heirs of Salvation, and again to relapſe into their former condition of Darkneſs, and being conſequently obnoxious to be infeſted by the Devil, and his Powers of Darkneſs. And that this was ſo, appeared by ſeveral ordinary Experiments in thoſe earlier Ages, not only of the Apoſtles, but that alſo of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who has many Examples of it in his Book <hi>de Lapſis.</hi> And this <hi>Confinement of the Spiritual Privileges</hi> of the peculiar People to the external Communion of the Church, as it was Fundamental to their Diſcipline, ſo it was rational conſequently to their other Principles. God was not thought obliged to confer thoſe Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, but by the Act of thoſe whom Himſelf had authorized to oblige Him. But <hi>Dividers</hi> were ſuppoſed not to belong to that Body to which the Promiſes were made; and ambitious <hi>Intruders</hi> into other Mens Offices could not in any Equity pretend to have their Acts ratified by God, from whom they could not be ſuppoſed to receive any Authority, when they did not receive it by the Rules and Orders of the Society eſtabliſhed by Him. Theſe things were then believed, and believed univerſally. Indeed nothing but an univerſal Belief of them would have maintained that Diſcipline, which was then obſerved in the Church; could have obliged them generally to ſuffer, as they did then, the ſevereſt Inflictions from the Magiſtrate, rather than incurr the much more feared Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Eccleſiaſtical Superiors. When we are alſo of the ſame Mind, and alike influenced by Principles and Regard to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, then indeed, and then alone, we may pretend to be a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity not degenerous from the great Examples of thoſe glorious Anceſtors: Then it will not be in the Power of Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to drive us from our Principles, and bring a Scandal on our Religion: Then where our Biſhops follow Chriſt, we ſhall follow them, and it will not be in the Power of the Worldly Magiſtrate,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64555:12"/>or the Gates of Hell it ſelf, to prevail againſt our Church, and to diſſolve the Union between us: Then Magiſtrates themſelves will be more wary of involving Conſciences on occaſion of their little Worldly Politicks; at leaſt they will not pretend Religion, and the Religion of that very Church which ſuffers by them for doing ſo. May we live at length to ſee that happy day! However it will hence appear how impoſſible it will be to excuſe our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries preſent Caſe from <hi>Schiſm,</hi> if it be tryed by that Antiquity which we do indeed profeſs to imitate and alledge.</p>
               <p>Now in this Caſe I am diſcourſing of, I have purpoſely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the Inſtances of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Age rather than any other, not only becauſe they are the Ancienteſt, indeed the firſt we know of, of one Biſhop's invading another's Chair not vacant; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have withall in him the moſt diſtinct account of the Senſe of the Church in his Age of ſuch <hi>Facts,</hi> and of the <hi>Principles</hi> on which they proceeded in condemning them. He had occaſion given him to be ſo diſtinct by <hi>two Schiſms,</hi> one of his own Church in <hi>Carthage,</hi> where <hi>Feliciſſimus</hi> was ſet up againſt himſelf; another (that I have principally inſiſted on) of <hi>Novatian,</hi> ſet up againſt <hi>Cornelius</hi> in <hi>Rome.</hi> On theſe Occaſions he has written one juſt <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſeveral <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> But theſe Principles were not ſingular and proper to that Age; they deſcended lower, and are inſiſted on by <hi>Optatus</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in their Diſputes with the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they diſpute the Queſtion of their <hi>Schiſm,</hi> without relation to their particular Opinions.</p>
               <p>We have here given them the ſenſe of the Church, in an Age wherein her Teſtimony is every way unexceptionable, wherein ſhe had certain means of knowing the Truth, and withall valued it as it deſerved. Even there we find the Principles now mentioned univerſally received, and univerſally received as the Grounds of that univerſal Catholick Communion, which ſhe had received by an uninterrupted Tradition from the Apoſtles to that very Time. Even there, I ſay, we find them received, where nothing could have been received univerſally that had been an <hi>Innovation.</hi> In ſo ſhort a time it was hard to bring in Variations from the Primitive Rule, and harder yet, that all the Churches could have been unanimous in them, if they had been Variations, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> reaſons in his <hi>Preſcriptions;</hi> eſpecially when there was no Univerſal Authority received over the whole Catholick Church that could induce them to it. From the Time of <hi>Trajan,</hi> the Succeſſion of our Saviour's
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64555:12"/>Family failed in the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to which all particular Churches paid a Deference. From the Time of <hi>Hadrian,</hi> there could be no pretence for that Church above others, when it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted not of <hi>Jews,</hi> but <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans.</hi> What was there there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that could make them unanimous in Variations, and Variations of ſuch Importance as this had been? They had then no General Councils: And <hi>the abſolute Supremacy of particular Biſhops in their proper Diſtricts,</hi> is by none maintained more expreſsly, and more zealouſly, than by St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> with particular regard to all other Powers, that in later times have pretended to oblige Biſhops; <hi>that is,</hi> to <hi>Councils,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> This <hi>Catholick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> grounded on the common Intereſt of all the Biſhops, to have all their Acts of Diſcipline in their particular Diſtricts ratified over the whole World, might have brought in other things that were conſequential to theſe common Intereſts. But there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing antecedent that can be imagined, that could have brought in this Catholick Communion of thoſe times, among ſuch a multitude of abſolute and independent Societies, as the Churches were then, if it had not been brought in from their very firſt Originals. And yet theſe Notions we were ſpeaking of were Fundamental to that Catholick Communion it ſelf, as managed in thoſe earlier Ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>That</hi> Intruders, <hi>or</hi> Anti-Biſhops, <hi>(by Lay-Authority) cannot be defended but by</hi> Principles fundamentally deſtructive <hi>of the Church, as a Society diſtinct from the State, in time of Perſecution.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF thoſe Errors, that deſtroy the very <hi>Being</hi> of the Church, as a Society, be Fundamental, I cannot for my part ſee how ſuch <hi>Anti-Biſhops,</hi> and all that own them, can be excuſed by Principles from Erring fundamentally. Their being Biſhops ſuppoſes ſuch Doctrines as, if they be once admitted, make it impoſſible for the Church to ſubſiſt as a <hi>Spiritual Society,</hi> whenever the State is pleaſed to perſecute it. They cannot poſſibly be ſuppoſed Biſhops of thoſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64555:13"/>Dioceſes to which they are conſecrated, till it firſt be ſuppoſed that their Predeceſſors are validly deprived, and conſequently that the Sees are vacant in Gonſcience. If it ſhould prove otherwiſe, the Clergy and Laity of thoſe ſame Juriſdictions will ſtill be obliged in. Conſcience, as much as ever, to adhere to their <hi>Canonical Biſhops</hi> till they be Canonically deprived, and to diſown ſuch <hi>Intruders</hi> as are put over them, not only without any Canonical Procedure, but without any Authority alſo that can oblige in Conſcience. The only Principle therefore on which they can pretend that their Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Biſhops have loſt their Right, as to Conſcience, muſt be the Power that even the <hi>Lay-Magiſtrate</hi> has to deprive Biſhops even with regard to Conſcience. If therefore they will defend their <hi>Schiſm</hi> by Principles, it will be neceſſary that they defend this Principle alſo, without which it is not poſſible that it ſhould ever be defended. They have no <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Judicatory,</hi> Juſt or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, that they can ſo much as pretend in this Caſe. And the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending this is that which will increaſe their Guilt, and will add to their charge of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> the aggravation of <hi>Hereſie</hi> alſo. For in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the aſſerting ſuch a Right as this to the Secular Magiſtrate, it will be neceſſary to aſſert that the Authority of the Church, even as to Spirituals, is, in Conſcience, the Right of the Civil Magiſtrate. If it ſhould not be ſo, then the Subjects of the reſpective Dioceſes may ſtill be at liberty in Conſcience to adhere to their deprived Biſhops. And if they may, they muſt, becauſe then all their former Obligations in Conſcience will ſtill hold as obliging in Conſcience to it is impoſſible that thoſe antecedent Obligations in Conſcience to adhere to their ſpiritual Superiors can be diſ-anulled, or diminiſhed by a Power that can pretend no Right in ſuch Matters with regard to Conſcience. But if we grant this Power to the Magiſtrate, this will perfectly overthrow the Church as a Society diſtinct from the State, and perfectly diſable it to ſubſiſt as a Society in a time of Perſecution. For when the Magiſtrate perſecutes it, it cannot then ſubſiſt as a Society without a Government, and a Government ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging in Conſcience, and not derived from the perſecuting Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. But if the Right of that ſpiritual Government be in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience the Magiſtrate's Right, it muſt be an invading the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate's Right to pretend to it, when he expreſsly forbids it. And if ſo, how can ſpiritual Governours in ſuch a Caſe pretend to it? How can they pretend to a Right that is none of their own, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtently with Conſcience? How can their pretending to it with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64555:13"/>ill Conſciences oblige their Subjects to adhere to them on account of Conſcience? Nay, how can it even excuſe them in Conſcience for not adhering rather to him whoſe Right it is ſuppoſed to be, and that even in Conſcience? No <hi>Neceſſity</hi> whatſoever can excuſe a Sin, much leſs lay an Obligation in Conſcience on Subjects to abet it, leaſt of all lay an Obligation on God to ratifie ſuch Acts of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as muſt be ſuppoſed no better than Uſurpations. And yet all Acts of Eccleſiaſtical Authority in a time of Perſecution can ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing if they be not ſuch as may oblige in Conſcience, and ſuch as God as well as Men is obliged to ratifie. Thus it had been Sin in the <hi>Romans</hi> to ſet up <hi>Cornelius</hi> (as plainly they did) not only without the Conſent, but againſt the Will of <hi>Decius.</hi> It had been Sin in him, and not in him only, but in all the Biſhops of his Age, to pretend to any Diſtricts in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. It had been Sin in them to exerciſe Authority in Diſtricts not belonging to them. Thus the Church had been perfectly diſſolved, as a Society at leaſt, within the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, unleſs we can ſuppoſe a Notion of a Society without Governours, without Diſtricts, without any lawful Exerciſes of Authority. And yet the Biſhops of thoſe Ages never thought themſelves obliged in Conſcience to go out of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire to retrieve the Power which is pretended to belong to them as Biſhops of the Catholick Church. And very probably it had ſignified nothing to have done ſo. They could have gone into no civilized inhabited Countries, but they muſt have expected Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates who could pretend to the ſame Right, as well as <hi>Decius,</hi> and who were as much diſpoſed as he to uſe their Right to the Prejudice of the Chriſtian Religion. What therefore would our Adverſaries have adviſed the Chriſtians of thoſe Ages to have preſerved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Society? Would they have had them retired into un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupied Wilderneſſes? But how could they make Societies there where there were no Numbers of Subjects requiſite to make a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety? Plainly therefore, the Catholick Church had then been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved as Societies, if theſe New Principles had been maintained in thoſe earlier Ages. And theſe ſame Principles do ſtill put it as evidently in the Power of the Civil Magiſtrate to diſſolve the Church, as a Society, within his own Dominions. For how can a Church continue a Society where Biſhops are in Conſcience de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their Spiritual Authority, and where Subjects are alſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved from their Obligations in Conſcience to obey them? And this is alſo a diſſolving the Catholick Church as to ſuch as live in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64555:14"/>ſuch Dominions, and as to any Benefits they can derive from the Catholick Church alſo. For Subjects of particular Diſtricts are no otherwiſe received into the Catholick Church, than as they derive a Right to Communion with all the Churches in the World, by their being admitted Members of the Churches of their particular Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricts. And they are alſo deprived of their Right of Catholick Communion when they are Excommunicated by the lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their particular Diſtricts. I cannot therefore ſee how our Adverſaries can excuſe themſelves herein from Erring fundamentally, if the Church's being a Society be admitted for a Fundamental.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Arguments <hi>and</hi> Objections <hi>againſt this Doctrine from Inſtances of Fact, and Publick Good, anſwered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AGAINST this truly Catholick Doctrine two things were oppoſed by the Adverſaries: The one, a Collection of <hi>Eighteen Inſtances</hi> of Biſhops, who being deprived, and not for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, did not inſiſt on their Right, or were not ſeconded by their Subjects, in the Hiſtory of 900. Years. Which <hi>way of Reaſoning,</hi> he ſhews, is neither <hi>Conſcientious,</hi> nor <hi>Prudent:</hi> For if Matters of Fact ſo nakedly related, without Evidence of the Principles on which they were acted, be urged as <hi>Precedents</hi> barely becauſe done, and no Oppoſition againſt them, it will be impoſſible to make any thing of ſuch arguing from Hiſtory. For what Hiſtory is there that in a Succeſſion of 900. Years does not afford Examples againſt Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples? And how eaſie were it for an Hiſtorian, by this way of Reaſoning, to juſtifie the Wickedeſt things that can be? (§. 9.) And in this caſe are divers circumſtances, which not appearing in any of the Inſtances make them inſignificant. §. 10-14. Nor do the Inſtances produced prove the Senſe of the Catholick Church, but only of the <hi>Greek,</hi> and eſpecially of <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> nor even of that Church in the firſt and earlieſt Ages, (§. 15.) but moſt of modern, barbarous, and divided Ages, § 22. and in different caſes, <hi>Part</hi> 2. §. 1. and the Deprivations, either by Synods, or diſagreeable to the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64555:14"/>Canons of that very Church, §. 8, 9, 11. and no ſuch Power ſo much as pretended by the Lay-Magiſtrate, §. 3. but the Emperors indeavouring to obtain their Wills by Authority of Synods; or by groſs Violence murdering, diſabling, or baniſhing the Incumbents.</p>
               <p>The other, their great Plea of the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> §. 47. which he well retorts upon them: That the <hi>Eternal Intereſts of Souls and of Religion</hi> are more to be valued in a Publick Account, than Worldly Politicks: That it is more the <hi>Publick Good of the Church, and of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> that <hi>Subordinations</hi> be preſerved, than that any particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be made a Biſhop by offering Violence to them; That the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Paſſive Doctrines</hi> of the Church be maintained in oppoſition to Worldly Intereſts, than ſeem proſtituted to ſerve them; That the <hi>Credit of the Clergy</hi> be maintained, than that they enjoy the Benefits of Worldly Protection; And that the <hi>Independency of that Sacred Function on the State</hi> be aſſerted, by challenging the Right, than that by yielding the Lay-Power ſhould be owned to have any Power of Depriving us of the Comfort of Sacraments in a time of Perſecution: And that this is more for the <hi>Interest of the State,</hi> even of the Civil Magiſtracy, than what is like to obtain upon the Ceſſion. Even the State cannot ſubſiſt without <hi>Obligations of Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Sacred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Oaths;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This hath reſpect to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the <hi>Sacred Vows of Canonical Obedience,</hi> for ſecuring that Right and Duty, where no Worldly Power can force them to it; which no other Power in the World can <hi>diſpence</hi> with, but that for whoſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt they were impoſed, and the dreadful Imprecations implied in them as an Obligation for Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</note> which can ſignifie nothing for the Security of any future Government, if they muſt ſignifie nothing for the time paſt. It is not for the Intereſt of the Publick to ſecure <hi>ill Titles</hi> in their Poſſeſſion, and thereby to incourage the Frequency of ill Titles, and frequent Subverſions of the Fundamental Conſtitutions, and all the Publick Miſeries that muſt follow on ſuch changes.</p>
               <p>But theſe things are more largely treated, and very ſolidly in the <hi>Defence of the Vindication,</hi> upon a farther occaſion. For the Adverſaries being ſo home preſſed with this, that they had little to reply, were forced to ſeek for <hi>new Arguments:</hi> And firſt, without any Anſwer to his Argument, and granting the Propoſition of <hi>the Invalidity of Lay-Deprivation,</hi> the Lawfulneſs of <hi>Submiſſion</hi> in the Eccleſiaſtical Subjects to Intruders, is only inſiſted on; and only from other <hi>Later Facts,</hi> and pretence of Peace and Tranquility of the Church. To which it is replied, that ſuch Submiſſion is <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> by the Law of God, makes the Subjects Accomplices in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and moreover in the Clergy, on account of their Oaths of canonical Obedience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and, That turning the Diſpute to <hi>later Facts</hi> draws it from a ſhort and deciſive, to a tedious and litigious Iſſue, with which there is no reaſon to comply. And concerning
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64555:15"/>
                  <hi>the Caſe of Abiathar,</hi> he ſhews, That the Fact is not commended in the Scripture as a Precedent; That the Magiſtrate could not, by the Doctrine of that Age, have any direct Power over the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; That in the Apoſtle's Age the Prieſthood was expreſsly owned to be far more Honourable than the Magiſtracy it ſelf; and, That <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Act was only of Force, and what God had threatned againſt the Houſe of <hi>Eli:</hi> Nor was <hi>Abiathar</hi> then the High-Prieſt properly ſo called, but <hi>Zadoc, &amp;c.</hi> Moreover, That <hi>Chriſtian Biſhops</hi> are properly Prieſts, and the <hi>Goſpel Prieſthood</hi> more noble than that of <hi>Abiathar;</hi> and that theſe Principles and Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences were admitted in the Apoſtolick Age, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Clemens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But the Principal Pretence of all is propoſed by another Author; That tho' the Argument holds where the State are Infidels, and ſo the Church and State diſtinct Bodies, yet not ſo where the State profeſſes the Chriſtian Religion: And, That the Benefits of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, of Honor and Profit, of Security, and of Aſſiſtance, which the Church receives from the State, require in Gratitude a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation. To which is replied, That more is required for ſuch a Power than meerly being Chriſtian, which gives no Title to any Spiritual Authority; That the ſame Perſons may be of diſtinct Societies; That the Church's Obligations are more neceſſary for the Subſiſting of the State, than thoſe ſhe receives from the State for hers; That the Benefits alſo received from her by the State, are greater than what ſhe receives from it; That a Pious Magiſtrate would not deſire ſuch a Recompence, if ſhe could grant it: But it is not in the Power of Eccleſiaſtical Governours to make ſuch Contract; Nor is it agreeable to the Mind of God that the Church ſhould ſo incorporate with the State. To which may be added, <hi>That the Catholick Church and particular States are, by order of Divine Providence, of different, unequal, and inconſiſtent Dimenſions: and, That Particular States are many intire, independent Bodies; but all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, Members of One great Body, and ſubject to the Supream and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Authority thereof; Nor ought any State, Prince, or Emperor, be admitted or reputed Chriſtian, who will not ſubmit all their Authority to the Authority of Christ in his Kingdom upon Earth; Which being the Chief of all Powers; who-ever reſiſts, reſiſts the Ordinance of God, and ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation,</hi> Rom. 13.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64555:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of the Authority of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>and that the</hi> Authority <hi>of the Primitive</hi> Catholick Church <hi>is greater than that of any Modern</hi> Particular <hi>one, and to be preferred before it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <q>THE laſt Refuge is <hi>Argumentum ad hominem;</hi> a poor Cauſe indeed that is reduced to that; which tho' tolerable as an Adjective with others more ſubſtantial, yet cannot ſtand alone, much leſs ſupport ſuch a Cauſe as this. <hi>Two things</hi> are alleadged, the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> &amp; <hi>Deprivation of the Biſhops in Q.</hi> Elizabeth<hi>'s time</hi> for refuſing that Oath, for Proof of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this caſe. To all this in general our Author oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>the Authority of the Church of Christ, the Catholick Church</hi> of the Primitive Ages; which the Church of <hi>England</hi> it ſelf admits: and, having ſet out the Objection fully, makes this Reply.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould moſt heartily congratulate the Zeal of theſe Objectors for our Church, were it really ſuch as it is pretended to be. But I can by no means commend any Zeal for any particular modern Church whatſoever, in Oppoſition to the Catholick Church of the firſt and pureſt Ages. We cannot take it for a <hi>Reformation</hi> that differs from that <hi>Church,</hi> which ought to be the <hi>Standard</hi> of <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> to all later degenerous Ages, at leaſt in things ſo eſſential to the Subſiſtence and Perpetuity of the Church, as theſe are which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the <hi>Independence</hi> of the <hi>Sacred,</hi> on the <hi>Civil</hi> Authority. Nor is it for the <hi>Honor</hi> of our dear Mother to own her <hi>Deviation,</hi> in things of ſo great Importance, from the Primitive Rule; much leſs to pretend her Precedent for over-ruling an Authority ſo much greater than hers, ſo much nearer the Originals, ſo much more Univerſal, ſo much leſs capable of Corruption, or of Agreement in any Point that had been really a Corruption. It is impoſſible that ever the preſent Breaches of the Church can be reconciled, if no particular Churches muſt ever allow themſelves the Liberty of Varying from what has actually been received by them, ſince the Ages of Diviſions, the very Reception thereof having proved the Cauſe of thoſe Diviſions. If therefore our modern Churches will
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64555:16"/>ever expect to be again united, it muſt be by <hi>Acknowledgment of Errors in particular Churches,</hi> at leaſt in ſuch things as have made the Differences, and which (whilſt they are believed) muſt make them irreconcilable. Such things could never proceed from Chriſt, who deſigning his whole Church for <hi>One Body,</hi> and <hi>One Communion,</hi> could never teach Doctrines inconſiſtent with ſuch Unity, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of Communion. And why ſhould a Church, ſuch as ours is, which acknowledges her ſelf <hi>Fallible,</hi> be too pertinacious in not acknowledging Miſtakes in her ſelf, when the Differences, even between Churches, which cannot all pretend to be in the Right whilſt they differ, and differ ſo greatly from each other, are a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <hi>Demonſtration of Errors</hi> in Authorities, as great as her own? Nor can any ſuch acknowledgments of actual Errors be prejudicial to Authority, where the Deciſions of the Authority are to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled not by private Judgments, but by a greater Authority. And if any Authority be admitted as competent for arbitrating the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Differences of Communion between our modern Churches, I know none that can ſo fairly pretend to it, as that of the <hi>Primitive Catholick Church.</hi> Beſides the other Advantages ſhe had for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Primitive Doctrines</hi> above any Modern ones whatſoever, ſhe has withall thoſe Advantages for a fair Deciſion, which recommend Arbitrators. She knew none of their Differences, nor dividing Opinions, and therefore cannot be ſuſpected of Partiality. And it was withall an Argument of her being conſtituted agreeably to the Mind of her bleſſed Lord, that ſhe was ſo perfectly one Communion as he deſigned her. And the Acquieſcence of particular Churches in her Deciſion, is eaſier and leſs mortifying than it would be to any other Arbitrator. To return to her, is indeed no other than to return to what themſelves were formerly before their Diviſions, or dividing Principles. So that indeed, for modern Churches to be determined by Antiquity, is really no other than to make themſelves, in their pureſt, uncorrupteſt Condition, Judges of their own Caſe, when they have not the like Security againſt Impurities and Corruptions. I cannot underſtand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how, even on account of Authority, our late Brethren can excuſe their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Zeal for even our Common Mother, the <hi>Church of England,</hi> when they preſume to oppoſe her Authority to that of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and of the Catholick Church in the firſt and pureſt Ages. I am ſure we have been uſed to commend her for her Deference to Antiquity, and to have the better Opinion of any thing in her Conſtitution, as it was moſt agreeable to the Pattern of the Primitive Catholick Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64555:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> Cranmer<hi>'s Opinion perfectly deſtructive of all Spiritual Authority, and his</hi> Authority <hi>in theſe matters none at all.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <q>FOR more <hi>particular</hi> Anſwer, he <hi>first</hi> ſhews the Author and Original, and ſo the Novelty, of theſe pernicious Opinions in <hi>England;</hi> and then anſwers to both the Allegations aforeſaid: the firſt not being very long, and therefore recited in his own Words at length, is as followeth:</q>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi>'s time, under whom the <hi>Oath of Supremacy</hi> was firſt introduced, the Invaſions of the <hi>Sacred Power</hi> were moſt manifeſt. Yet ſo that even then they appear to have been <hi>Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Invaſions.</hi> But who can wonder at his Succeſs, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the violent ways uſed by him? So many executed by him for refuſing the <hi>Oath?</hi> The whole Body of the <hi>Clergy</hi> brought under a <hi>Premunire,</hi> (for doing no more than himſelf had done, in owning the <hi>Legatine</hi> Power of Cardinal <hi>Wolſey</hi>) and fined for it, and forced to Submiſſions very different from the ſenſe of the Majority of them? He did indeed pretend to be adviſed by ſome of the Eccleſiaſticks, as appears from ſeveral of their Papers ſtill preſerved. But they were only <hi>ſome few ſelected</hi> by himſelf, never fairly permitted to a freedom and majority of Suffrages. And when even thoſe few had given their Opinion, yet ſtill he reſerved the Judgment of their Reaſons to himſelf. And to ſhew how far he was from being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, thoſe of them who were moſt open in betraying the <hi>Rights of their own Function,</hi> were accordingly advanced to the higher degrees in his Favour, and were entruſted with the Management of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs. None had a greater ſhare in his Eccleſiaſtical Councils than Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer.</hi> Nor is there any who, upon all the Queſtions propoſed, wherein Eccleſiaſtical Power was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, does more conſtantly ſide with the King's imperious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt <hi>the true Rights of his own Order.</hi> He allows the King the Rights even of <hi>Preaching the Word,</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtring the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and allows neither of them to the Eccleſiaſticks, any further than as they derived them from the Prince's <hi>Lay-Commiſſions.</hi> He
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64555:17"/>permitted indeed their <hi>Conſecrations,</hi> as he had found them, by thoſe of their own Order; but derives nothing of their Power from thoſe Conſecrations. He makes the <hi>Ceremonies of Conſecration</hi> indifferent things, no way concerned in conveying the Spiritual Power. That he derives wholly from their <hi>Lay-Deputation.</hi> He gives them a Power of <hi>Preaching the Word,</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtring the Sacraments,</hi> where the Lay-Powers allow it, and he allows them neither where the Secular Magiſtrate forbids them. They muſt <hi>admit</hi> whom the Laws oblige them to admit, and they muſt not <hi>excommunicate</hi> any whom the Secular Laws take into their Protection. The <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his being a Lay-Man, may perform theſe Offices him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if he pleaſed. And the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks,</hi> notwithſtanding their Conſecration, are not by him permitted to perform them, unleſs the Magiſtrate be pleaſed to give them leave. Nay, ſo far he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds in his <hi>Flattery of the Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> that he allows no more <hi>Gifts of the Holy Ghost,</hi> in the <hi>Laying on of the Hands of the Presbytery,</hi> than in the collation of any Civil Office. Even in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, he rather excuſes than commends all the Exerciſe of their Spiritual Authority, as neceſſitated to it by the Exigency of their preſent Circumſtances. As if any Neceſſity could excuſe Uſurpation. As if any Exerciſe of a Power not belonging to them could have been ſeconded by ſo viſible manifeſtations of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as that was which was exerciſed by the Apoſtles. Yet even their Authority he makes perfectly precarious. He owns no Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation on the Conſciences of the Chriſtians of thoſe times to obey even the Apoſtles themſelves, but aſcribes their Obedience then wholly to their good Will, ſo as to leave it to their own Liberty, whether they would be ſubject or no. And why ſo? Only becauſe the Apoſtles had no Civil Empire. This wholly reſolves all Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Conſcience into Civil Empire, and makes it impoſſible for the Church to ſubſiſt as a Society, and a Communion, without the Support of the Civil Magiſtrate. Accordingly the ſame Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> took out a <hi>Patent</hi> for his Epiſcopal Power,
<note n="*" place="margin">And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before from King <hi>Henry,</hi> long before <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: from which; and from the Compoſure, it is plain who was the Projector.</note> preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Biſhop <hi>Burnet,</hi> full of a Style ſo pernicious to Eccleſiaſtical Authority. He there acknowledges all ſort of <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> as well <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> as <hi>Civil, to have ſlowed originally from the Regal Power, as from a Supream Head, and as a Fountain and Spring of all Magiſtracy within his own Kingdom.</hi> He ſays, <hi>they who had exerciſed this Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction formerly,</hi> (for which he took out this Patent) <hi>had done it only</hi> PRECARIO, and that <hi>they ought with grateful Minds to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64555:17"/>this Favour derived from the King's Liberality and Indulgence, and that accordingly they ought to yield whenever the King thought fit to require it from them.</hi> And to ſhew what Particulars of Eccleſiaſtical Power he meant, his Patent inſtances the Power of <hi>Ordering Presbyters,</hi> and of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Coercion,</hi> meaning (no doubt) that of <hi>Excommunication.</hi> Nay further, the ſame Patent gives him a Power of Executing, by the King's Authority, thoſe very things which were known to have been committed to him by God himſelf in the Scriptures, <hi>per &amp; ultra ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae tibi ex Sacris Literis divinitus commiſſa eſſe dignoſcuntur.</hi> By which we underſtand, that <hi>no Branch of Spiritual Power whatſoever was except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Yet all this Grant was to laſt no longer than the King's Pleaſure. I know not what the Lay-Encroachers themſelves can deſire more. Here is ſo little Security for the Church's ſubſiſting, when the Secular Laws diſcountenance her, as that ſhe is not allowed the ſame Liberty that other Subjects have, of pleading the Secular Laws already made in favour of her; but is left expoſed to the Arbitrary Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Prince, which is thought hard in the caſe of other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. This Yoke the Politicians have lately impoſed on the <hi>Church of Scotland:</hi> GOD, in his good time, releaſe her from it.</p>
               <p>I have often wondred how the moſt learned Biſhop <hi>Stilling fleet,</hi> who firſt publiſhed the fore-mentioned Papers, as far as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> could think them conſiſtent with his own Principles: They are ſo perfectly contradictory to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning <hi>the Power of Excommunication</hi> ſubjoined in the <hi>Second Edition</hi> of the <hi>Irenicum,</hi> and indeed to the Doctrine of the <hi>Irenicum</hi> it ſelf, as far as it was conſiſtent with it ſelf, or with any one Hypotheſis. For ſometimes he ſeems to doubt whether there can be any <hi>Power</hi> properly ſo called without <hi>Coercion,</hi> or any <hi>Coercion</hi> without <hi>external Force.</hi> As if indeed the Fears of the future Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs attending Excluſion from the <hi>Privileges</hi> of <hi>Church Communion</hi> had not been, in the pureſt Ages of the Chriſtian Religion, more properly <hi>Coercive,</hi> than the fear of any Evils that were in the Power of the Secular Magiſtrate. It is certain, that good Chriſtians then choſe rather to ſuffer any thing the Magiſtrate could inflict, than <hi>Excommunication.</hi> But I more admire, that ſuch a <hi>Betrayer of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Rights</hi> ſhould, by our Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtorian of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> be propoſed as the <hi>Hero</hi> of his times, and as Exemplary to ſuch as might, in his Opinion, deſerve the Name of Heroes ſtill. Yet he calls it a <hi>ſtrange Commiſſion</hi> in Biſhop <hi>Bonner,</hi> when he took out a Commiſſion from the King as to his Spirituals, conceived in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64555:18"/>the ſame terms with that of <hi>Cranmer,</hi> in the Particulars now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. He grants that
<note n="*" place="margin">It is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Charge upon <hi>Bonner,</hi> but falſe; &amp; diſproved both by this, which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Cranmer</hi> the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and by Evidence of Fact, that he and others took out ſuch Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bonner.</hi> v. <hi>A. Harmar. pag.</hi> 51, 52. The Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to excuſe <hi>Cranmer</hi> caſt the <hi>Odium</hi> of it upon <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed a reaſon to render it credible.</note> 
                  <hi>Bonner</hi>'s Inducement to take out that Commiſſion was, that it was obſerved, that <hi>Cranmer</hi>'s great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the King was chiefly grounded on ſome Opinions he had of the Eccleſiaſtical Officers being as much ſubject to the King as all other Civil Officers were. Yet <hi>Cranmer</hi> was to be excuſed, becauſe that if he followed that Opinion at all, it was <hi>out of Conſcience.</hi> Why he ſhould doubt, whether he was of that Opinion, I cannot gueſs, when himſelf has publiſhed thoſe very Papers of the learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> wherein Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> does ſo plainly own himſelf of that Opinion; when he has alſo publiſhed <hi>Cranmer</hi>'s own Commiſſion to the ſame purpoſe. As little Reaſon I can ſee why he ſhould ſay, that <hi>Cranmer</hi> was once of that Opinion, as if he had afterwards retracted it. The Papers upon the Conſult were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi>'s time, in the Year 1540. And then, even by the Biſhop's Obſervation, the Change of his Opinion had loſt his Intereſt with the King, if his Intereſt had been grounded on that Opinion. But <hi>Cranmer</hi> kept to the ſame Opinions in the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Sixth.</hi> Then it was he took out his Commiſſion. The young King himſelf ſeems to have been of the ſame Opinion, in his <hi>ſecond Paper of the Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Collections,</hi> which I can aſcribe to nothing more probably than to the Inſtructions of his God-Father. Nor does it appear the Arch-Biſhop chang'd his Mind afterwards. The only thing inſiſted on by our Hiſtorian to prove it, is his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing a Book ſet out ſoon after, which teaches the contrary. But having already ſhewn that he ſtill retained the ſame Opinion in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Sixth,</hi> his Subſcription cannot prove any change of his Opinion, but that he complied, whatever his Opinion was, when he found his non-compliance could not hinder the contrary Opinion from being acceptable. But indeed that Book was not ſo clear in that point that his Subſcribing it would argue any change from his former Opinions. But our Hiſtorian ſays, that when <hi>Cranmer</hi> maintained that Opinion, he did it out of Conſcience. Perhaps it might have been ſo. But I am ſure it is but an ill Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove it ſo, that <hi>his Intereſt in the King was viſibly promoted by it.</hi> Yet if he had frequently followed Opinions contrary to Worldly Intereſt, that, I grant, might have been an Argument, that tho' his Intereſt was indeed promoted by this Opinion, yet that might have been no Inducement to him why he did imbrace it. But, on the contrary, in the great Actions of his Life, it was the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceableneſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64555:18"/>of his Opinions to the Princa's Deſigns that principally recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. It was notoriouſly <hi>his Opinion for the Divorce</hi> from Queen <hi>Katherine,</hi> that <hi>first brought him into the Court,</hi> and into the King's Knowledge. Nor is it denied by our Hiſtorian that it was ſo. And in the Caſe of <hi>Proſuming Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Marriage from Bedding, he gave <hi>contrary Judgments</hi> concerning the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with Queen <hi>Katherine,</hi> and that with <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Cleve,</hi> exactly according to the King's Inclinations, and his own Intereſt in gratifying them. In Queen <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi>'s Caſe he allowed it for a good Preſumption, but not ſo in the Caſe of <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Cleve.</hi> Nay, when the <hi>Proteſtant Reformation</hi> it ſelf was againſt <hi>his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> with the Prince then in Poſſeſſion, he <hi>ranounced even that.</hi> Nor did he recant that <hi>Recantation,</hi> at leaſt he gave no publick Signification of his recant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, till he was aſſured by Dr. <hi>Cole,</hi> in a Sermon before him at St. <hi>Maries,</hi> that even his Compliance ſhould avail him nothing for the Saving of his Life. And even in that compleater Collection publiſhed by Biſhop <hi>Burnet,</hi> none of the other Biſhops or Divines conſulted on that Occaſion is ſo <hi>perpetually thorough-paced</hi> for the King's Inclinations as he was. Which <hi>Singularity</hi> alone, not only againſt the Intereſts, but the Suffrages of his Function, in Favour of <hi>Encrcachments,</hi> ſufficiently ſhew how far he was from being Impartial in Queſtions of this Nature.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Having given this account of the Worthy Author of this Doctrine, and of his Principles, he proceeds farther to ſhew, That it is not the Intereſt of the Church, that his Authority in theſe things ſhould be regarded; That neither He, nor the <hi>Duke of Summerſet,</hi> did deſerve the <hi>Elegies</hi> by our Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtorian beſtowed upon them, nor the Hiſtorian himſelf any great Commendation or Thanks for his miſtaken Service in it; That there were <hi>many</hi> in thoſe Reigns, under which the Reformation was tranſacted, who very much <hi>promoted the Reformation,</hi> but <hi>with no good Deſign</hi> on Religion or Reformation; as K. <hi>Henry</hi> himſelf, <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> who both at their Executions declared themſelves of the <hi>Roman Communion;</hi> That <hi>the part acted by</hi> Cranmer was not really contributive to a Reformation; but if his Principles freed the Church from the Tyranny then in being, they naturally introduced a Tyranny of more pernicious Conſequence, which perfectly deſtroys the Government of the Church, and thereby diſſolves the Society, which was the thing to be reformed; That as little reaſon there is for that advantageous Character he gives his other Hero, the Duke of
<note n="†" place="margin">This is but part of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege he was guilty of: and nothing of what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in Church Lands and Churches themſelves for his own uſe.</note> 
                     <hi>Summerſet;</hi> for he was one that advanced the Sacrilege of the former Reign againſt <hi>Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> and in the time of his Protectorſhip againſt the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> themſelves; and wrote a very angry Letter to Biſhop <hi>Redley</hi> for oppoſing his deſigned beginnings of it in the Suppreſſion of <hi>Clare-Hall:</hi> and how could he reconcile any true Zeal for Religion and the Church, with his Sacrilegions Deſigns (and Practices too) againſt that very Church, whoſe Communion was owned by him?</p>
                  <p>After this he ſhews, from the ſeveral Acts of Parliament, how <hi>the Impious Notion</hi> of the <hi>Supremacy</hi> was by degrees ſettled by that Authority, and continued in the Reign of Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> who lived not to the Maturity of Judgment to diſcern the <hi>Falſhood and ill Tendency of thoſe ill Principles</hi> ſo deſtructive to all Religion, and to the very Fundamentals of the Church, as it is a Society and Communion, which had been inſtilled into him by his God-Father <hi>(Cranmer,)</hi> who was always the moſt forward Promoter of them.</p>
                  <p>And thus far our Author hath proceeded very clearly: but his more particular Anſwer to the two Objections being not fully concluded, but ſtill under Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64555:19"/>a more compleat account of that is reſerved for another Occaſion; but may be expected ere long. And in the mean time to do him right, and gratifie the Reader, we ſhall conclude with the recital of part of a §. of the <hi>Vindication,</hi> (which had been altered without his Conſent) according to his Mind and Original Manuſcript. It is § 25. <hi>Pag.</hi> 71. <hi>as followeth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>— neither did the Emperor think that his own Authority was alone ſufficient for the purpoſe.
<note place="margin">Calinicus <hi>by having his Eyes put out was incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by that Incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deprived of his Office without a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</hi>
                  </note> The way that was taken to <hi>deprive</hi> him was the ſame that was uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally taken to deprive Emperors, without taking away their Lives, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding being the <hi>ſupream</hi> Authority, were never thought deprivable by any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Exerciſe of Authority. That was not by a <hi>Legal Sentence,</hi> but by reducing them to a natural Incapacity for Government, by putting out their <hi>Eyes.</hi> This perfectly diſabled them to judge of the <hi>Decrees</hi> to be ſubſcribed by them, without which it was impoſſible for them to govern. Nor was it ever thought <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndatiful</hi> to deny ſuch Princes Subjection; whatever their <hi>Right</hi> was otherwiſe, when they once come to be ſo incapacitated, however they came to be ſo. No more than if they were Lunatick. Incapacity was alone ſufficient for that. And this Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city was ſo notorious, that we never read that even the Princes themſelves, who had been thus incapacitated, did ever judge ſo partially even in their own Caſe, as to think fit to reſume. Such a Caſe therefore as this did not put it in the Power, even of <hi>partial Subjects,</hi> to deny their Duty where it ought not to have been denied, by judging Incapacities where really there were none. And thus the Law never deſigns an Office for a Perſon <hi>incapable</hi> of it, where the <hi>Incapacity</hi> is ſo notorious as that it cannot be falſly applied by corrupt Interpretations. Thus therefore that Emperor deprived this Patriarch <hi>Callinicus</hi> by putting out his Eyes. Nor was this ſuch a <hi>Maiming</hi> only as had made him at firſt unfit to be <hi>elected,</hi> but ſuch as <hi>diſabled</hi> him to <hi>hold</hi> his <hi>Office,</hi> tho' the Emperor had never taken it from him, however he had come to it by a Diſeaſe, or by any other Providence. It was not like <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſs</hi>'s biting of the Ear of <hi>Hyrcanus.</hi> That only unqualified <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> for holding the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> by the particular <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which allowed none for <hi>Prieſts</hi> who had any ſuch corporal ſmperfections. Nor was it like the ſlitting of the <hi>Noſe</hi> of this Emperor <hi>Juſtinian.</hi> That only deprived him of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the graceful and Majeſtick <hi>Preſence</hi> becoming a Prince; but was ſtill conſiſtent with the Eſſential Qualifications for Government. But this Blindneſs perfectly diſabled our Patriarch <hi>Callinicus</hi> from ever Exerciſing any Patriarchal Office, eſpecially that moſt eſſential one of our Chriſtian <hi>Euchariſtical Sacrifice,</hi> and no Law could ever deſign to keep an <hi>Office</hi> perpetually, unleſs by allowing a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual unextinguiſhable <hi>Right</hi> in a Perſon who is under a perpetual <hi>natural</hi> Incapacity of <hi>Exerciſing</hi> it. Thus therefore there was no need of a <hi>depriving Sentence</hi> againſt <hi>Callinicus</hi> when he was under this <hi>Incapacity,</hi> himſelf could now pretend no <hi>Right</hi> to an <hi>Office</hi> which he could never hope to be able to <hi>exerciſe.</hi> What Pretence therefore could he have for <hi>Separating</hi> from the <hi>Communion</hi> of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> when him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was <hi>diſabled</hi> from <hi>Officiating</hi> in any <hi>Communion?</hi> What pretence could the <hi>Church</hi> have for Queſtioning the <hi>Ordinations</hi> of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> when his <hi>Rival</hi> was not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of exerciſing any <hi>better Ordinations?</hi> But, God be praiſed, this is none of our preſent Fathers Caſe. They are not under any ſuch <hi>Incapacities.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
